

# Dr.KhushbuParihar

Ph.D. (Life Science)

- Navi Mumbai, Maharashtra
- Indian

## Skills

Microbes culturing

Molecular biology

Antimicrobial pound discovery

com-

Chromatography

**Basic Biostatistics** 

Microsoft Office tools

**English** 

Hindi

# **Biography**

I am a Microbiology and Plant biology researcher with 5 year of work experience on Microbes. I am a scientific thinker who enjoys solving problems, analytical, highly organized and hard working.

I have done research on thermophilic and halophilic actinomycetes isolates from Rajasthan for their isolation, molecular characterization, and antimicrobial screening as a Ph. D. Scholar with CSIR-UGC JRF. While pursuing my Ph.D. I also got the opportunity to get involved in research related to fungus diversity and antifungal protein purification and characterization from leguminous plants. Further, I engaged in writing various research papers on my work for reputed journals like the International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, Current microbiology, Biologia Futura, and many others. My main role involved research on extremophilic actinomycetes with management of microbiology lab including Culture maintenance, Instrument handling, Stock maintenance, teaching to graduates and postgraduates students, and conducting practical exams for them.

I attended a training program on Polyphasic characterization of bacteria conducted by CSIR-CCMB, Hyderabad for one month.

I am looking for an opportunity for teaching plant science and microbiology to graduates and post-graduate students.

# Work experience

#### Research scholar | PhD student

12/2016 - 01/2022

Department of Botany (Prof. Praveen Gehlot) Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur

Working on the isolation and identification of halophilic and thermophilic actinomycetes from saline habitats of Rajasthan and screening of their antimicrobial potential against human pathogen.

#### Training and skill development program

01/2018 - 02/2018

Analysis of Microbial Diversity and Polyphasic Characterization of Bacteria (Dr. GSN Reddy/ Dr. Archana B Siva)

CSIR-Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Hyderabad

Training on the polyphasic characterization of bacteria using phenotypic, chemotypic and genotypic methods.

#### Part time lecturer

01/2017 - 06/2020

Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur Subject: Botany and Microbiology to PG/UG students

#### **Secondary Teacher**

07/2015 - 07/2016

St. Anthony's Senior Secondary School , Jodhpur Subject: Science to secondary students

# **Education**

12/2016 - 01/2022

Life Science (Ph. D.)

Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur

Microbiology

Molecular characterization and antimicrobial potential of thermophilic and halophilic actinomycetes isolates of Rajasthan".

07/2013 - 05/2015

#### Botany (M.Sc.)

Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur

Specialization - Plant Microbe Interaction .

07/2010 - 05/2013

Life Science (B.Sc.)

Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur

Chemistry • Botany • Zoology .

07/2009 - 05/2010

# Shri Sumer Senior Secondary School, Jodhpur

Physics • Chemistry • Biology .

### Interests

- Traveling
- Singing
- Drawing
- Reading

## **Contact**

- □ +91 8619448164
- pariharkhushbu93@gmail.com
- researchgate.net/K.Parihar
- ✓ linkedin.com/Khushbu Parihar

## **Publications**

- Parihar K, Gehlot P, Mathur M, Tak A, Pathak R and Singh S K. (2022). "Species Composition and Diversity Dynamics of Actinomycetes in Arid and Semi-arid Salt Basins of Rajasthan". In: *Current Microbiology*, 79, 168.
- Parihar K, Tak A, Gehlot P, Pathak R and Singh S K. (2021). "Molecular characterization of Nocardiopsis species from Didwana dry salt lake of Rajasthan, India".
  In: Journal of Applied and natural Science, 13 (1): 396-401.
- Kumar S, Solanki D S, Parihar K, Tak A, Gehlot P, Pathak R, Singh S K. 2021.
  "Actinomycetes isolates of arid zone of Indian Thar Desert and efficacy of their bioactive compounds against human pathogenic bacteria". In: *Biologia Futura*.
- Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Tak A, Gehlot P, Pathak R and Singh S K. 2020. "Characterization of a novel antifungal protein from Acacia senegal seeds". In: *Journal of Environmental Biology*, 41: 607-612.
- Gehlot P, Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Tak A, Pathak R and Singh S K. 2020.
  "A new record of gastroid fungus Broomeia congregata Berk. from Great Indian Thar Desert, India". In: *Indian phytopathology*, 73; 111–115.
- Gehlot P, Sharma K, Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Pathak R and Singh S K. 2018. "Identification and characterization of antibacterial bioactive compounds from an edible gastroid mushroom Phellorinia herculeana". In: *Journal of Mycology and Plant Pathology*, 48(2018): 178-182.
- Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Tak A, Gehlot P, Pathak R, Singh S K. 2018. "Characterization of a novel seed protein of Prosopis cineraria showing antifungal activity". In: *International Journal of Biological Macromolecules*, 116(2018): 16-22.
- Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Sharma K, Gehlot P, Singh S K and Pathak R. 2018. "Purification and characterization of a novel thermostable antifungal protein with chitinase activity from mung bean (Vigna radiata)". In: *Journal of Environ*mental Biology, 39: 406-412.
- Meghwanshi G K, Kumar S, Solanki D S, Parihar K, Sharma K, Gehlot P, Singh S K and Pathak R. 2017. "Isolation and enzymatic characterization of Streptomyces isolates from western Rajasthan". In: *Plant Archives*, 17 (2): 929-934.
- Gehlot P, Sharma K, Solanki D S, Kumar S, Parihar K, Pathak R and Singh SK. 2017. "Hitherto unknown green mould disease of edible Gastroid mushroom Phellorinia herculeana (Pers.) Kreisel". In: *Journal of Mycology and Plant Pathology*, 47 (2): 232-233.

Navi Mumbai, 27th April 2022